Welcome back to the second lecture week.
Now, I want to start today by working
a bit with this whiteboard here.
So, drawing a few things or writing down
a few things, later switching to slides.
And in particular, I want to start by discussing
a few notions, a few concepts that in some
sense are, of course, very
familiar to you, and very obvious,
but maybe in the distinction between programming
and mathematics, there are some subtleties
that I want to discuss.
And in particular, this will lead also to
distinctions I later want to make in the slides.
So, let's talk about variables, functions,
expressions, commands. And the latter two
are the two things that I particularly
want to focus on later in the slides.
Okay, but let's start with some obvious notions,
like, what is a variable? And of course,
a variable is something that you see all the
time, whether in math lectures, or in programming,
so, a variable is
something like this x. Let's say we write
a function: f(x) is x squared plus one.
So, that's a variable, of course (the x).
Likewise, you, of course, will know variables
from programming, maybe in a C- or Java-
like language.
And similarly so in an untyped language, like Python, just
that you wouldn't write the explicit "int" (integer) here.
Let's say we introduce a variable. Its value is
zero at the beginning, then maybe we print it out
in some way, depending on what exactly the
procedure is for doing that in our language,
but something like a 'print'
function probably exists.
And then I increment this i-value and print
it again, and maybe I write for-loops, etc.
So, that's how you work with variables.
And that's also not something new to all of
you.
But of course, then there are also many
other uses in logic and mathematics.
So, for example, you write or use
variables and expressions like this.
So, in set theory, we say something like "you
want to have the set of all even numbers".
And you could do this by saying, well, let's take
two times x for every x from the natural numbers.
So, that's a use of variables.
In logic, we have things like quantifiers where
you could say, well, "for all x, it should
hold" or "it does hold for certain predicates
that if [p(x) and q(x)] holds, then it also
holds that some other predicate r is true
for x."
Or we write equations with variables, maybe [2
* f(x)], for the function from above, is 20.
And then we know ways of solving this by discovering
what the x is, or we have expressions and
also know some expressions where we say
something like "let's take all the values
from zero to ten,
and sum them up." Or in the spirit of equations,
we can also have systems of equations.
So, for example, one thing we sometimes want to
do is finding solutions for equations like this.
Well, let's take two variables now, then,
you know, with linear equations, it's enough
to have two equations over these two variables to,
in most cases at least, solve this for x and y.
So, we’re considering this as one system of equations.
And all these are cases and uses of variables.
Well, there’s nothing new
or surprising here, I think.
However, there's actually one thing
that is different between one of these
examples and almost all the others, and
that's exactly the programming example.
So, what's a bit strange, compared to all the
other examples here, is that in programming,
the i might be different
in these two places, right?
So, it's not the case that i is zero and again zero.
No, these two print statements do different things.
And that's not the case
in all the other examples.
Why is that?
So, if you calculate, say, here, of course,
the x might vary because we want to take
every x from the natural numbers, but then in
the expression here, we have only one value.
What do I mean by this?
For example, we could replace this [2 * x]
with [x + x], and of course, even though
there are now two occurrences of x, whenever
we choose one x, we would expect that these
two occurrences of x are the very same thing.
So indeed, we expect that whether we write
this [2 * x], or [x + x], the set should be
the same mathematically. That's a trivial
thing.
But it's an important difference between
this example and all the others.
Likewise, here, we do have two occurrences
of x.
But of course, in order for this system of
equations to even make sense, we expect that
both x's are the same value.
Otherwise, we wouldn't be asking to solve
this system of equations if you don't expect
that while x and y might be different,
of course, x in both lines is the
same, and y in both lines is the same.
Okay, that's something different
between programming and mathematics.
That's, first of all, just an observation.
And, of course, this doesn't mean that
every x is always the same, right?
Of course, by saying all of x (all x), we
want this to be true for many different x, but
in the scope, once we have chosen one x here,
then in the scope of the expression of the
formula, each x should be the same.
And that's not the case in imperative
programming here; the scope would
be opened by this declaration of the i.
And then all these parts of the program are in
the scope of i, so they are in the syntactic
region in which i is defined, and still
different i here will have different
values and different results.
Okay, so that's different between this
programming example and all the others.
Okay, maybe we should simply, for the moment,
take this and come back to that and what it
means for programming or functional programming
in comparison to other paradigms later on.
Okay, variables.
So, let's move on to functions.
That's also something that you
know and shouldn't be surprising.
So, let's look at functions.
Okay, what do we know about functions?
What are typical functions?
Well, the "f of x equals x squared plus one" [f(x) = x^2 + 1]
from above, that was, of course, a typical mathematical function.
And you know what you can do with this; for
example, you can evaluate it for some input,
and then you get, in this case, 26,
because five squared [5^2] is 25.
And you get 26.
And maybe you should just say
what the type of the function is.
So, typically, in most parts of
mathematics or analysis, at least, we talk
about functions on the reals.
So, this would be a function
from the reals to the reals.
And actually, given that it's a square and
plus one, we can even say that it goes
from the reals to the positive reals only.
So, it cannot be zero or even negative,
the result will always be positive
(just as in this case).
Okay, so that's the function, and then
we build expressions over functions.
What does this mean?
We build in more complex mathematical terms
built from, for example, function calls.
So, we could say something like: "f of five, plus
f of five" [f(5) + f(5)], and we know that it's 52
because it's the same as two times f of five
[2 * f(5)] and f of five is 26. [f(5) = 26]
Okay, nothing surprising here.
And of course, we can do the same thing more
generally, even with a variable, it would be
true that f of x plus f of x [f(x) + f(x)]
is the same as two times f of x [2 * f(x)].
Even though x is a variable, whatever we
put in for x, this statement will hold.
Why?
Because in the given scope, x is fixed.
Again, very different from what we saw
above, for the "print(i)" example, right?
That was completely different.
There, we didn't have that
"print(i)" as always the same thing.
Okay, now you could say, well, in the case
of print i, it doesn't even make sense to
say something like print i plus
print i [print(i) + print(i)], right?
So, where is the contradiction?
Well, let's look at a different example.
Let's say we don't want to print, we want
to read stuff, then of course, we could have
a situation that we, for example,
want to have an expression like this.
So "read()", and maybe we have to give an input
there to say what you want to read. But let's
say we always read integers. So,
we don't even write anything there.
Then we could have an expression like this.
And we could just say I don't
want to give an argument there.
And that's definitely not the same in any
imperative language that you probably have
in mind to do something like this.
Why is this? Because on the left-hand side,
I would read two values, maybe five and seven
and then I would add them up: five
plus seven is 12 [5 + 7 = 12].
On the right-hand side, I would only read
one value, maybe the five and then double
it, and the result would be 10.
And I wouldn't even read the second value.
So definitely, these are completely different
expressions of programs, much in contradiction
to what we saw over here.
Okay, should we be worried about this?
Apparently, C programmers are not overly worried
about things like this, because that's exactly
what they do, writing programs in this style,
or with these features, one might say maybe
it's very specific about 'read' and 'print'.
So, we have to be careful when we do read or
print, and for all the other things in the
language, we are closer to mathematics.
But that's not actually true.
Once you say, well, it's just special
functions that behave like this.
In C, and essentially also in Python, all functions
are special in that sense, because whatever
you do, you might always have
these kinds of side effects.
Even if you don't read or print directly,
you can have assignment statements, etc.
So basically, all syntactic parts, or small
expressions might have side effects, which
lead to situations like we see here.
Okay.
Why is this a problem?
Why could this be considered a problem?
Well, we give up all kinds of tools from mathematics,
if we accept that the same expressions, even
though containing the same variables,
actually lead to different results.
What would be some examples from mathematics?
Well, all kinds of manipulations of formulas, and
you will see that functional programming
is basically about manipulating formulas.
As opposed to imperative programming.
Let's take an example.
And let's, again, take this function from above. We
had: "f of x is x squared plus one" [f(x) = x^2 + 1].
And we had this other expression.
I say something like two times
f(x) is 20 [2 * f(x) = 20].
And the typical task in algebra or an arithmetic
part of a math course, very simple math,
would be to solve this for x.
What would we do?
Well, for example, you could say, well,
let's use the definition of f(x), right?
Something like two times x squared
plus one is 20 [2 * (x^2 + 1) = 20].
And then you would solve
this by doing small steps.
And here, if we additionally have
maybe said upfront that x should be
a positive real, then we can really simply take
the square root here, and we would have solved this
for "x equals three" [x = 3].
And of course, this really makes sense.
Saying that this now must be the solution of
what we had above, because we have performed
equivalence steps only, makes sense because
we assume and simply take as given that each
x in all these lines is the same. It's a variable, but
in the scope of our calculation, it shouldn't change.
Again, not true for the i-example with the
assignment statements in my assumed C or Java
or whatever program we saw above.
Okay, and of course, the same is true, if
we manipulate systems of equations again,
if we solve this with linear algebra methods,
then, of course, again, we must use and assume
that in the scope of this system of equations, x is
always the same thing, y is always the same thing.
Okay, so that's the fundamental difference between
programming in an imperative language and mathematics.
And now, the main message of today's lecture will
actually be that programming in a declarative
language like Haskell (as we start with; but also later
in Prolog it is like that) is like this mathematical
way of looking at things (in particular
at variables and expressions).
So, in some sense, all Haskell programming is
like manipulating equations as we have seen here.
Of course, not for f of x and square
[f(x), x^2], but for our domains.
For example, Pictures in our first CodeWorld
tasks and examples, but of course later arbitrary
data structures. The point is programming in
Haskell is basically about writing equations
and transforming expressions and solving
equations or looking for solutions.
Okay, evaluating expressions and similarly
will later be less the case for Prolog
well, and with a different background, more in
terms of the earlier example where I talked
about logical formulas rather
than somehow expressions.
But, again, with this idea that we manipulate
expressions or formulas and not execute commands,
which might change, for example,
the assignment of variables.